Mm-hmm.
Where were we up to?
Item 14.
14.
Copyright.
Yeah. Gotcha. Thank you.
Just switch back from-
Yeah
... all the things you were just working on to
Exactly.
Sorry, I was on the wrong one. I was on the-
No, it's all right. Yes, good to see you.
Joanna's on.
Oh, she's online. Excellent.
Joanna, I think just double check we've got you there.
Yep. Apologies, I don't have a working web camera at the
moment.
Oh, no. Not a problem at all. We can hear and see you.
So look, welcome to the Social Services and Community Select Committee this
afternoon. We've got you for five minutes
on the Copyright
Bill. So, time is yours when you're ready to go.
Well, thank you to the committee for hearing me today.
I
am wanting to talk about this bill in two ways.
Both
that
satire and parody have been a
pillar
of
democracies, republics,
a way for individuals and
organizations to have their say on
society and on their governance
for millennia. Some of the
earliest
satire that we have is
in Roman texts and Aristophanes from 400
BC. So-
Well,
this is not something that needs to be
looked at as, "Oh,
shock, horror, people are
making fun of people." This has
happened forever, and I think this tradition should continue
and be allowed to continue as
freely
as possible. Because if you
can't criticize your government, if you can't make fun of
those in power,
then that just detracts from
the functioning of that government in
some ways. The other thing that I would want to bring up in
relation to this bill is,
while
it's a good bill, I like it, I would like to see
greater clarity about who
can operate
under that bill. So,
if individuals have rights under this bill in terms of
satire and parody, or if businesses,
where is the line between what is just fair use
and what
becomes a commercially sensitive issue?
So for instance,
if I, in my business, was to
do advertising that kind of makes folks fun at
other competitors' advertising, similar to
the famous Coke versus Pepsi
advertisements overseas,
where does the line get drawn? And it would be great to
have greater clarification and opportunity
for businesses and societies
to basically
state, "We are safe saying this. We're not going to be sued
or treated as
libelous or anything because we are making a joke,
because we are saying,
'Hey, you see this thing? Let's make
light fun of it
to be able to, as part of our advertising.'"
So, there's been cases
recently where not-for-profits supporting
various communities have poked fun at
other organizations that have
been negative towards those communities
by
just tweaking their branding and making
light of their position. That should be
allowed. You shouldn't
be able to just be
spreading utter falsehoods.
But at the same time, there should be a degree to which,
if I want to
reference
another organization or another business
in a way that doesn't demean that other business
dramatically, while still poking fun at them,
that should be totally fine. And that's
also how
advertising and business has been done
for centuries. So,
from a political standpoint, it's a tradition millennia old, and
we should support
reinforcing the ability to undertake that.
And from a business standpoint, it's also
going to make things better for everyone.
All right.
If there's any questions.
No, we don't have enough time, but thank you very much, Joanou, for coming and
making a submission this afternoon.
Thank you for your time, and please pass this bill.
Thank you.
All right, our next submitter is Mr.
Tim Batt, also via
Zoom.
Kia ora. Okay.
All right. Yep, no, we can see and hear you.
So, look, welcome to the committee, and we've got five minutes with you this
afternoon. So the time is yours when you're ready.
Wonderful. Kia ora, everybody. My name's Tim Batt.
Thanks for the time here on the committee.
I'll be reading from prepared notes just so I can keep my thoughts in order.
Bit of background on me. I've been performing stand-up comedy for close to
20 years. I've been both the co-chair of the New Zealand Comedy Guild and a
director of the New Zealand Comedy Trust, which is the governance body that
operates the New Zealand International Comedy Festival.
I've been making TV, radio, podcasts, and live shows for about a decade
and a half now.
I submitted in support of this bill because our country is absolutely
brilliant at comedy, and I find it crazy that we're so out of
step with basically every other country on Earth when it comes to protecting parody
and satire in our Copyright Act. As you will likely already know, the
USA has got a specific fair use clause in Section
107 of their Copyright Act, protecting parody.
The UK, Australia, Canada have a fair dealing for
parody protections in their copyright laws.
And even the European Union, under its EU InfoSoc directive, provides member
nations with a parody protection legal framework for their copyright
laws. What you might not be aware of, though,
is the real-world effect for the
lack of legal protection
for parody and satire,
the effect that it has in New Zealand, because it does have a very real effect.
The reason I found out that we have no, well, a real lack of free speech
provisions in our copyright laws is when I was first writing for TV, for
Jono and Ben, and was told by our producers that everyone in the entertainment
industry is essentially winging it When it comes to
parody of copyrighted entities like famous movie franchises and characters.
So we were given instructions to never go too far with jokes in that direction
because legally we have no protection if it ever gets tested.
Oh.
Hopefully, I don't have to explain to you how insidious it is that in the comedy
environment have a lack of legal protections any time we
might reference a brand name, a well-known company, or a famous character.
TV producers, networks, and broadcasters in this country
have had a history of being very broke,
and that means that the threat of legal action means a lot of ideas that may even
potentially be perceived to be in the neighborhood of brushing up against the
Copyright Act will get shut down in pre-production.
This has happened, and I'd like to give you an example.
I've had a lot of ideas shut down in the writers' rooms of TV shows over the
years, but one particular one I want to highlight actually happened to two
friends of mine, Joseph Moore and Laura Daniel, both of whom are incredibly
talented. They work on "SNL UK" now, and they're actually
editing a brand new TV show that just got filmed here in New Zealand at the
moment. They perform as a comedy pop duo called Two Hearts.
Now, at the New Zealand Comedy Gala, which is a televised live event that kicks
off the comedy festival each year, they performed a really brilliant parody
song that was stylistically referencing Disney's "Moana." And I
say stylistically referencing because they specifically went to
pains to make sure that they complied with the existing and incredibly
onerous copyright laws of New Zealand to make sure that they did not fall afoul
of it. They did their due diligence to ensure that they did not infringe on
Disney's rights under New Zealand's current laws in any
way. They performed the song, everyone in the room loved it, and then
TVNZ's legal team, who by my estimation acted completely out of
fear rather than any serious legal rationale, stopped the performance from
getting broadcast on TV. Again, the work did not infringe on anyone's
copyright, but our laws are so lacking in protection that our
broadcasters are financially terrified of legal action from big
rights holders, and they censor stuff anyway.
Not only did that brilliant work of comedy get prevented from being broadcast and
it was withheld from the public, this also meant that Two Hearts didn't get paid
for it because your payout gets based on how much of your performance gets
televised.
Mm.
So I wanted to give you a real-world example of not just the
direct lack of legal protection, but the chilling effect of our laws
being so out of step with the rest of the world.
I will
end it there, but I just can't emphasize enough my personal
recommendation and advocacy for this bill's adoption. Thank you.
Thank you, Tim. Appreciate that. Look, just a quick question from me.
We heard, I think it was last week, from the organization that
represents about 3,000 creatives in New Zealand, and just
concerns they had about this bill.
I think they were broadly in support of the objective, but the
operationalization of this bill, they had some serious concerns about it not
protecting
the creatives that they represent. Do you have any comments on that?
No. I don't sort of have enough expertise to comment on that in the moment.
Okay. No. Not a problem.
When's your next show, Tim?
Tonight.
Hey.
Well, break a leg, as they say.
Thank you.
Thank you very much. Much appreciated.
I got to-
Thanks, folks
... appreciate it.
Thank you.
Cheers.
Law Students Association online as well.
Excellent.
All right. Good afternoon and welcome to the New Zealand Law Society Association.
Jasmine?
Thanks, Joseph. Thank you. Tena koutou katoa.
My name is Jasmine McTavish, and I'm appearing on behalf of the New Zealand Law
Students Association. We are the national representative
body for all law students across Aotearoa.
We provide advocacy and a united voice on all matters that affect our
legal students. As with Tim, I'm going to be reading off some notes
that I quickly formulated upon being informed that it was only a five-minute
speaking time. So NZLSA does-
No, we've got you for 10, we've got you for 10 minutes.
Okay, fantastic. Cool. Mm-hmm. So NZLSA does
support the bill in principle, as set out in our
submission, particularly in recommendation one.
We consider this to be an overdue modernization of our New Zealand
copyright law.
We understand that our current framework doesn't provide sufficient certainty
for creators engaging in forms of expression that are
increasingly common in our modern society.
However, our position is that the bill is an
important first step, but that it requires further refinement
to ensure that it operates effectively in practice.
The reason that this bill matters to the people that we represent is that
students are often at the forefront of new forms of creative expression,
whether it's a law review parodying a popular song, a
student publication that may be using satire to comment on current
political issues, a young creator producing
online content, or students that are regularly engaging with
parody and satire as a way of communicating their beliefs, their ideas and
their values.
And to the students that we represent, these aren't simply forms of
entertainment. They're ways that we're able to participate in public
debates, to engage with our political issues, and to help develop
our legal students' creative skills.
However, we've identified that students and emerging creators often
do this without access to any kind of specialist legal advice or any
resources that larger organizations may have available to them.
And this uncertainty is a problem that we believe this bill has the
opportunity to address.
As discussed in part five of our submission, the current law
creates a chilling effect. Our current
framework looks at the fair dealing concept,
and this creates a relatively narrow idea
compared with the jurisdictions of Australia, Canada, the
United Kingdom, and the United States as well.
Because there's currently no specific exception for parody or
satire,
creators that are making any kind of content need
to try and
fit their work within any kind of existing category, and that might
be criticism or maybe review.
And this does create a kind of uncertainty for our
courts as well.
For our students, our independent artists, and our emerging
creators, a copyright dispute can be something that's really costly and
intimidating, and this might stop them from expressing their
views because they don't have that access to any kind of legal
advice or any kind of understanding of what it is that they may
have in front of them if they are to be found to be breaching
what this bill is proposing. And this is where the connection with the
freedom of expression becomes really important.
So Section 14 of the New Zealand Bill of Rights Act recognizes the
importance of our freedom of expression.
And we're not suggesting that copyright protections should be weakened or that
creators should lose any kind of control over their works,
but rather that there is a balancing and
a maintenance of the appropriate balancing.
We believe that copyright should be protective and should protect
creativity, but it shouldn't necessarily prevent others or any
kind of form of legitimate creativity, any kind of criticism, or
any kind of commentary.
So NZLSA has identified several ways in which we believe that this bill could
be strengthened. And the first would be being through clearer
guidance around the definitions of parody,
satire, and fairness.
Also, as outlined in recommendation two, we recommend that the
bill provides a non-binding statutory guidance on the
meaning of parody and satire. We know that these
concepts are inherently contextual, but providing
any kind of guidance would assist both the creators and copyright
owners, and maybe more importantly, the courts in
making Parliament's intention clearer.
Our concern is that without any kind of guidance, courts may face
uncertainty or unnecessary uncertainty when
determining whether any kind of particular work qualifies.
When looking at recommendation three,
we understand that the bill appropriately requires that the use
must be fair, but it currently provides very limited guidance
on what that fairness requires.
Therefore, we have recommended that a non-exhaustive fairness framework
could be created drawing on some of the existing copyright
principles, and some of those relevant factors that could be included
could be the purpose of the use, whether the work is transformative,
the nature of the original work, the amount of original work that's
used, and the effect on the market value for the
original works.
So the purpose of these factors isn't to create a rigid test as such.
It's just to provide a practical framework that protects copyright
owners while also allowing some kind of genuine parody and satire
to operate.
We also want to highlight recommendation five, which relates to the practical
operation of this exception online.
Much of our parody and satire occurs through digital platforms, especially
with the students that we represent.
However, these online platforms often rely on an
automated copyright enforcement system and standard terms of
service, and this creates a risk that statutory rights created by
Parliament could be undermined by practice and by
private arrangements.
A creator may have a lawful exception under the legislation
but still have their content removed because of a platform's broader
protections.
So we recommend that a potential protection against
contextual override be created.
The final issue that we want to highlight is in recommendation four,
and that relates to Tikanga Māori and Te Tiriti o
Waitangi obligations or considerations.
We consider that this is an important opportunity for this bill to reflect
the very unique legal context of
Aotearoa.
We understand that our traditional copyright frameworks
have largely focused on individual ownership and our economic
interests. However, as recognized by the Waitangi
Tribunal and Wai 262, there can sometimes be a
mismatch between these concepts and the collective nature of
both our taonga and Mātauranga
Māori. And this is really important because parody and
satire often involve radical or criticism.
And where taonga Māori are involved, potential harm
isn't usually economic. It might relate to mana,
whakapapa, cultural authority, and the responsibilities of
kaitiaki.
And these considerations aren't always captured through our traditional
copyright concepts that are focused on that market value.
So our recommendation here isn't to prohibit parody from
involving any kind of Māori content, but rather to ensure that our
courts are able to consider Tikanga Māori and Te Tiriti
principles when it's relevant when assessing fairness.
And going back to fairness, we know that it, again, is inherently contextual,
especially here in Aotearoa. That context includes that
unique constitutional environment.
Thank you for your time, and I welcome any questions.
Oh, thank you, Jasmine. We have our first question from Maude.
Thank you, Ms. Chair. Jasmine, thank you for your really
well put together submission.
I just have a question around recommendation three, and in
particular, D and E, and just wonder if you
can give some guidance about how that could be quantified.
I'm sorry, one moment.
Sorry, I'm just pulling this up now.
Okay.
Which page are you looking at there, Maude?
It's on page eight.
Page eight.
Thanks.
Recommendation three, D and E, and how it could be quantified.
Yes.
I believe that when looking
at the amount and substantiality
of the part of works used,
there needs to be a balance when looking at the market
value of the original work,
and then also probably weighing up
the intentions behind the
creator's use of that, and whether that balance
justifies.
Thank you very much, Jasmine. I would love to ask you some more questions, but we
are at time now. But look, I just want to thank you for making a very
comprehensive written and oral submission.
Thank you.
Thanks, Jasmine.
Right, our next submitter
is...
Matthias. In person.
Welcome, Matthias.
Real person.
So welcome, come forward and take a seat there in the middle if you like.
All right, welcome. We have five minutes with you this afternoon, so the time is
ready.
Okay.
Kia ora, thank you so much for giving me the opportunity to talk to you.
I can't say that I'm an expert in governance or in legal matters.
I came to New Zealand, Aotearoa, in '94 to work on Te Papa
Tongarewa, the national museum, on the design team.
I'm an industrial designer by trade, and I also
lecture at Massey University. So rather than being in the regulatory
space, I'm a maker of things.
And so my submission is less about technicalities and
more about contextual things as I experience them from my profession.
And I want to speak to two points in my submission.
They are the benefits of dissent.
But first, I would like to reflect on the intentions and the
imperfections of intellectual property
protection, specifically copyright.
To me, both notions,
dissent
and
where parody and
satire are part of, and copyright seem to be
sitting in a weird unlogical relation to each other,
like apples and cows, and I'd like to split them up and share separate thoughts and
concerns on each.
I understand intellectual property, specifically copyright, to refer to an
author's exclusive right to benefit from the expressions of
ideas.
When it comes to expressions of ideas, we seem to overlook
fundamental notions that have been widely understood
before copyright even existed, and that is, in reality,
ideas exist everywhere. They are there for everyone to
receive, to hold, to do something with, to share.
And also another notion that ideas are complex, they are
interconnected, they are never singular.
Now, how did we end up with copyright?
When Gutenberg and others introduced movable type in Europe,
it accelerated the printing and the spreading of ideas and the expressions of
ideas throughout Europe. Printers found
that their expressions of ideas would be ripped off,
and so we began to treat ideas as singular and as
property. And while it is a clunky
approach, it was deemed reasonable that somehow the IP
legal frameworks could give that author or the inventor
a fair go to get a return on investment.
But it is clunky. And, as with many things,
that are simple or intended to be simple, absurdities
will always follow with it.
We won't go too much into that. But it promoted the
evolution of visual and material culture in Europe,
as diverse expressions of diverse societal values.
So that is a point that I find very important in how ideas are being
protected.
Now, the emergence of machine learning
is leading to the circumvention of those protections.
And there are only very few beneficiaries, and it is at the
expense of most of us.
IP is being harvested and rehashed to the lowest common
denominator.
Earlier in the advent of public
internet There was the promise of access, the promise of
unlimited proliferation of diverse expressions of ideas.
That was the big dream that was going to happen, and the opposite is
happening.
Media expert Dr. Claire Robertson gives evidence that while there are
exceptions, most people worldwide have begun to severely
narrow and conform their areas of interest,
their norms, and beliefs. That is the measured result of the
introduction of the internet. Mm. There's pros and cons to everything.
Now, when we look at AI, that has only accelerated that very
same diminishing effect.
So unless there is political will,
the 19th- and 20th-century-based IP
laws seem toothless in the face of this
at the expense of diversity, critical reflection,
collective wisdom,
and diversity as a fundament for democracy.
Can we please update our laws to protect this?
That's my first point. Okay. Then about parody and
satire. Parody and satire are important political
activities. They are there to balance or to challenge what
is overpowering. They are there to hold those who are in
charge to account, to draw spectacular attention at
times to critical voices when those in power, and
their mates in the lobby, do not like the messenger.
McKinsey researchers say that it is an important factor in
successful governance, is engaging with dissent.
Dissent is useful. It should not be stifled by
improprietary rules. To use copyright rules to
stifle sincere dissent
is anti-political. It opens the door to power abuse.
It happens in societies where democratic checks and balances have
been removed. These are the places where people try to run away
from fast.
Just to conclude,
when
copyright laws exist to what we deem
a reasonable chance, to give a reasonable chance to
authors before getting ripped off,
stick with that,
and do it well,
especially when current laws do not do enough to protect small,
medium-sized entities, designers, artists,
people of the public, just anyone.
And when the appropriating, the exploiting, and the
misrepresenting of customary knowledge, I'm not digging
into Y262 here- Mm. The person before me has done that
beautifully.
And it's done by the most wealthy organizations on the planet.
We'll have to draw to a closing time.
Yep.
We are well over time.
I fully support the amendment to the Copyright Act.
Thank you very much. Thank you for coming, making a submission this afternoon.
Thank you.
We next have Professor Graham Austin, also in person. Welcome.
Graham, welcome. We have five minutes with you this afternoon.
Oh, great.
Thank you for your written submission as well.
Thank you very much to speak with you today.
As you've seen from my written submission, I strongly support
the bill. I think it's the poster child for a
good defense for copyright law. A whole lot of things come together.
It's consistent with the aims of copyright law and that parodies are new works of
authorship, and we want to encourage creativity, and so it
aligns with those basic aims. As other speakers have said, it's a
free speech safety valve,
that these are typically criticism, social commentary, taking the Mickey out of
things. These are good things in a free and democratic
society.
And for a parody to do its job, it has to take quite a lot of the
underlying copyright work. Otherwise, the parody won't work.
And so that's another reason why a defense is needed, and we can't rely on
other parts of the Copyright Act. And as I explained in the written submissions, it
also solves or goes some way to solving a
market failure problem. The Copyright
Act's very clear. It says in Section 14, copyright is a
property right, and in a society like ours, we tend to
say that property owners have the right to decide what happens with their
property, whether they license it to other people, whether they monetize it, and
so on. It's their choice. The problem with parody is that most
people don't like to be lampooned, and so we can't
rely on the copyright owners to enter into a licensing
market for parodies. So this is one of those rare opportunities
or rare instances where it's good for the law to step in and give
people a nudge towards allowing these
parodies. And the final reason is, I think
it brings our laws into line with Australia, Canada, broadly with
the United States, and with the EU.
If you go back to the first reason and say this helps encourage
the creation of new works, if our laws align with other countries, that
takes away some of the transactional friction when people
want to market their parodies into other markets.
We want people to have international distribution deals for their creative work,
and that lowers the friction.
I suspect a number of other submitters have said the bill as currently
drafted is too narrow, and that it needs to
extend to audiovisual works. And I put some
suggestions in the written submissions.
It may be aimed at the officials to help people think through how that might be
achieved in a neat way so that the bill
that comes into select committee is
broadly consistent with the bill that comes out of select committee.
I want to talk about definitions because there has been some discussion about
whether definitions of these concepts are required in
the act. We heard that from Jasmine's submission just a
moment ago.
I don't think that's a good idea. If we are starting A
few years ago, maybe. But in the case law
from other countries, the judges are very good at sorting out what is
a parody, what is a satire.
And our judges and the people who write guidance for creative
workers can draw on that quite easily.
And it might muddy the waters if we try and do this,
and also bring in some inconsistencies in our law, which could
create some of that legal and transactional friction.
So, I think that's
not necessary. And also, we need to remember
that this is fair dealing for the purposes
of parody and satire. And so, that fairness question is
really important. And overseas, judges are really good at
asking what is really the basic question here, which is
should this content be licensed or not?
And that's the basic question here.
It's not so much does it fit into the category of parody or
satire or, in the EU, pastiche, et cetera.
So, I think avoiding definitions, too, is probably
a good thing.
My final point is about moral rights, and there was some discussion
of moral rights. A really good discussion in the first reading of the bill.
In most mature legal systems, moral rights and parody live
together quite happily, and that's also a product of
having parody tightly defined, so that it's very
clear that it's not the original author's work.
It's actually the parodist doing that.
And when that's clear, then it doesn't prejudice the honor and
reputation of the underlying author.
So, I think that the existence of moral rights in our
legislation is not a problem for the successions.
In sum, I'm in favor of it. It's something that's discrete,
and doesn't need to wait for the broader copyright reforms that have been
announced by the government in the wake of the two free trade
agreements.
Might I ask you a really very quick question on that, because we heard last week
from the We Create Alliance, which represents,
I think, 40 of New Zealand's creative industries and organizations representing
30,000 Kiwi creators,
et cetera,
their view was that although change was needed, they thought it
should be through a comprehensive best practice policy development approach.
And a
comprehensive review of the Copyright Act was important,
and their concern of this would be, basically, in
their words, an ad hoc approach to dealing with one discrete issue.
Mm-hmm.
Any comment on that?
Go back to the point, I think that this sits alone and is
needed, and the other kinds of reforms that have been announced,
such as getting rid of the three strikes regime,
the introduction of blocking orders, those kinds of things are not going
to affect the parody and satire
defense that's been proposed in this bill.
So, I think they're separate issues, looking at what
has been announced by the government.
Great. Well, thank you very much for coming-
Thank you
... and making submissions. I have to thank the rest of the commission as well.
Thank you.
Right, that concludes public submissions on this bill this afternoon.
Is there anyone else?